<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse the 24. of October. 1624. By Robert Bedingfield Master of Arts, and student of Christ-Church in Oxford</title>
            <author>Bedingfield, Robert, 1597 or 8-1651.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07538</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1792</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101420</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837234</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837234</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1549</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07538)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1549)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 698:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse the 24. of October. 1624. By Robert Bedingfield Master of Arts, and student of Christ-Church in Oxford</title>
                  <author>Bedingfield, Robert, 1597 or 8-1651.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Lichfield and William Turner, for Henry Cripps,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On Romans VI, 23.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1549:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1549:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT PAVLS CROSSE THE 24. OF OCTO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BER. 1624.</p>
            <p>BY ROBERT BEDINGFIELD Maſter of Arts, and Student of <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> in Oxford.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>Oxford seal</figDesc>
               <p>AC: OX</p>
            </figure>
            <p>OXFORD, Printed by IOHN LICHFIELD and WILLIAM TVRNER, for HENRY CRIPPS. 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:1549:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>modern(?) bookplate</figDesc>
                  <p>Academiae Cantabrigiensis Liber</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1549:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL HIS VERY WORTHY VNCLE SIR THOMAS RICHARDSON Knight, Serieant at the Law, grace and peace be multiplied in CHRIST IESVS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et mee humblie beg of you, that you would bee pleaſed to take this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon into the Sanctuary of your patronage: your free and gracious promiſe to be the Patron of the Author, hath imbol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened him to intitle you ſo to his iſſue. The violence of a wet ſeaſon denied it ſome Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, which it might haue had, your incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging
<pb facs="tcp:1549:3"/> command to haue a ſight of it, &amp; the forcible importunity of wel-wiſhing friends haue preſſed it, and giuen it readers which I intended it ſhould not haue had. I apologize not, if it bee better to preach, 'tis good to print: the vnderſtanding is not informed, nor the will moued alwaies by the Eare, but ſometimes by the Eye; otherwiſe the ſuttle Romaniſts would vnclaſpe the Bibles of the Laitie, and not denie them to read the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. I know your deuotions and your im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploiment; God and your Countrie permit you not in the tearme-time to read a long Epiſtle. I conclude therefore with my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to almightie God, that as he hath indow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you with his more eminent graces and richer gifts, ſo he would put it into the heart of the King to reward them, that your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours may one day ballance your deſerts, &amp; that in the meane time your dwelling may remaine (as now it is) the oracle of the citie.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my ſtudy in <hi>Chriſt-Church, in</hi> Oxford.
<date>Nouemb. <hi>24.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your moſt humbly deuoted Seruant and Nephew <hi>ROBERT BEDINGFIELD.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1549:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>ROMANS 6. VERSE 23.</bibl>
                  <p>For the Wages of Sinne is Death, but the Gift of God is Eternall life through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Embaſſie (Right Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the reſt Beloued) I know not whether it bee fuller of horrour or delight, whether it may more amaze or comfort you, the firſt part like the ſeuere threats of the puniſhing Law, ſearcheth the wound; the latter, like the ſoueraigne balme of the ſauing Goſpell, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the cure; 'tis equally diuided, the firſt woundeth not ſo deepe, but the latter cureth as faſt. If the wound be vnto <hi>death,</hi> the cure is vnto <hi>life: If the wages of ſinne be death, the gift of God is eternall life, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Text naturally is thus put on ſunder, there is a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and there is an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>The wages of ſinne is death,</hi> there is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; but <hi>the gift of God is eternall life through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord;</hi> there is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. In the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, there is firſt <hi>malum culpae,</hi> the offence gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; <hi>ſinne;</hi> ſecondly, there is <hi>malum poenae,</hi> the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1549:4"/> inflicted: <hi>Death,</hi> thirdly, there is the Iuſtice and proportion betweene the offence and the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſtipend, <hi>the wages;</hi> fourthly and laſtly, there is the certainty of the puniſhment to bee inflicted, intimated in the verbe of the preſent tenſe, it <hi>is</hi> death, <hi>The wages of ſinne is death.</hi> In the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, there is firſt life, oppoſed vnto death in the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by his adiunct or duration, it is <hi>eternall;</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, heere is the meanes of conferring of it on them that receiue it, which is not by way of wages, as death in the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <hi>freely and by gift;</hi> thirdly, heere is the doner, hee that beſtoweth it, <hi>GOD.</hi> Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, heere is the Mediator, hee through whom, and for whoſe ſake it is giuen, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> This is my modell, theſe my parts: briefly, God hath this day ſet before you <hi>life</hi> and <hi>death,</hi> good and euill, now that you be not deceiued in your choice, giue me leaue to lay them open vnto you; firſt, the euill, <hi>malum delicti, &amp; malum ſupplicij,</hi> the euill of Sinne, and the euill of death, <hi>The wages of ſinne is death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Man in his Original &amp; Primitiue perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, being the Son of God, by creation, as he ſummed vp the world in an Epitome, ſo was he a liuing Image of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers glory,<note place="margin">De eo quod de terius potiori inſidiari ſoleat. Auguſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de Gen. cap. <hi>8.</hi> &amp; praeter Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uius ſententiae fuit Lactantius, lib. <hi>2.</hi> Inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itut. diuin.</note> whom he beſt copied out in his better part, his ſoule; not that it was <hi>ex traduce,</hi> from God, not that the Diuinity was rent in two, or diuided, ſo that that became part of the Diuine Eſſence, as firſt <hi>Philo</hi> the Iew doted, and after him the <hi>Maniches</hi> blaſphemed: there was no tranſ-fuſion, but a creation, no identity, but a conformity, which was not in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but in quality: neither was the ſoule alone ſo
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1549:4"/> glorious, but the body alſo, which was firſt made a houſe for the ſoule to inhabit, and not a priſon to ſuffer in; a houſe indeede made of clay, but made by the immediate touch of the God of Heauen, a ſublu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary body, yet not waited vpon by corruption, a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect where contrary qualities did reſide, and yet not a ſubiect ouer which they might triumph; Laſtly, both ſoule and body were ſo vnited and married to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, that corruption being not able to poſſeſſe the parts, nor to diſſolue the vnion, the whole man was immortall, and that not by the dowry of grace, but by the priuiledge of Nature, not ſupernaturally, as were the garments of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the Wilderneſſe, or as <hi>Auſtin</hi> coniectured concerning <hi>Enoch</hi> &amp; <hi>Elias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> de pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. meritu, &amp; remiſſione cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> but <hi>per ſequela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> naturae,</hi> ſo that immortality was part of his Nature, as well as his nature was euer immortall; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall not abſolutely or eſſentially, for ſo hee had been a God; not by creation poſitiuely, for ſo had he beene a ſpirit; but negatiuely, ſaith the Schoole, and conditionally, he had the priuiledge, <hi>poſſe non mori,</hi> although he had not the immunity, <hi>non poſse morï;</hi> as there was a poſſibility of dying: ſo it was without a neceſſity.</p>
            <p>I follow not the Sententiaries, which follow not their Maſter, but are curiouſly inquiſitiue to know what ſhould become of man, if hee had not fallen: how he ſhould haue preſerued himſelfe from Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, whether by eating of the tree of life, or by any other meanes, we know no more then our Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>diſtinct.</hi> 23.</note> and he (ſaith <hi>Lombard) Accepit ſcientiam &amp; praeceptum eorum quae facienda erant, non accepit prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiam
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1549:5"/> eorum quae futura erant.</hi> Wee know not what he ſhould haue eaten, to haue preſerued his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, we know what he did eate to loſe it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adami homicida gula.</hi> The eating of the forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fruit diſmantled and ſtript our firſt Parents at once, both of their roabes of Righteouſneſſe and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality: that firſt ſinne made a breach in the well-ordered Oeconomy of the ſoule: proſtrating reaſon at the feet of ſenſe, and enthroning paſſion in the chaire of reaſon: there was now no longer harmony betweene the fleſh and the Spirit; the motions of the fleſh, rebelling againſt the rules of reaſon, the ſterne of reaſon being neither pliable to the ſpirit, nor the ſpirit obedient vnto God: this diſorder bred diſeaſes, the ſummoners and fore-runners of death, ſo that man was preſently retrograded into the element of duſt, of which hee was firſt compoſed. Death as it was threatned for ſinne, ſo was it inflicted vpon ſinne, <hi>The day that thou ſinneſt thou ſhalt ſurely die, Gen.</hi> 2.17. and the day that hee did eate, ſurely hee did die, the Mother and the Daughter, Sinne and Death, are both of an age, he was afterward but a mouing car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe, a walking ſepulcher, <hi>Mortuus erat, non mortalis,</hi> as a malefactor is a dead man when he is condemned, before he is executed.</p>
            <p>Euery ſinne is of the ſame nature with the firſt, and bringeth death like that; indeed it murthereth not with the ſame extent: that was the ſinne of nature, and therefore the death of nature, ſo that afterward wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men brought forth children,<note place="margin">Chryſolog. Serm <hi>111.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vindictae ordine, non na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae. Lucbant peccatum mundi qui mundum non noue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1549:5"/> &amp; parentis ſui ſoluebant poenam, cuius vix vitam deguſtarunt.</hi> Other ſinnes are perſonall, and therefore the deſtruction of the perſon; be it ſinne in the roote, or ſinne in the branch, be it the mother and ſpawne of ſinne, <hi>inbred pollution,</hi> or the fruit and harueſt of ſinne, <hi>actuall tranſgreſsion:</hi> the firſt hath many branches, and all deadly, the other hath many Species, and all mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall; in the firſt there is <hi>participatio culpae, imputatio reatus,</hi> and <hi>concupiſcentia,</hi> and all are rewarded with death, euen the laſt, which is not onely the cauſe of ſinne, and the puniſhment of ſinne, but ſinne it ſelfe; be it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not onely where conſent is added to luſt, but where luſt is without conſent; not only actuall concupiſcence, but habituall, naturall, and originall; not the ſecond motions only, or <hi>concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia formata,</hi> as the Schoole ſpeaketh; but <hi>motus primò primi,</hi> and that which is <hi>informis:</hi> yea, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it preuenteth the vſe of reaſon, although it be reſiſted by the power of the ſpirit: ſhall the trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor ſuffer that committeth the Treaſon, and ſhall the plotter and contriuer eſcape? or ſhall the laſt eſcape puniſhment, becauſe the firſt will not offend?</p>
            <p>Originall ſinne hath not more branches, then actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all hath ſpecies; neither are theſe leſſe fatall then the other, whether they be ſeated in the vnderſtanding, as the darkeneſſe of errour concerning God; or in the heart and will, as our irregular thoughts, and exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant deſires; or in our outward members, as externall actions, whether they be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, treſpaſſes againſt the rules of Nature; not ingrauen in ſtone, but imprinted in the conſcience; ſo the <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſinned, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1549:6"/> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, treſpaſſes againſt the word written, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.4. ſo the Iewes offended both theſe, whether they be of omiſſion or commiſſion, not onely the obliquity of our actions, but our vnlawfull ſurceaſe from action, not our words, but our ſilence alſo. The Advocate whoſe lips are ſealed vp with a fee of the aduerſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; the Prieſt, not whom Authority, but ſloth hath ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenced, ſhall both be rewarded with death, and they therefore deſerue their wages, becauſe they haue not done their worke. There is no ſin of omiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is not a ſinne of commiſſion; <hi>ſi non pavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti, occidiſti:</hi> he that ſeeth his neighbours Oxe fall into the pit, and helpeth him not out, he puſheth him in; not to ſaue a man when we may, when we ought, in the Court of Conſcience is to murther a man. If I ſhould reckon vp all ſorts of ſinne, I ſhould commit one againſt your patience, yet could I ſhew you none, whoſe iſſue is not death.</p>
            <p>If the Eye but luſteth, <hi>mors per feneſtras;</hi> if the foot but ſlippeth, <hi>praecipitiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt,</hi> there are no ſtaires but fall we muſt into the pit, and wee ſhould downe to the bottome, were it not bottomleſſe. Hee that doth but peeuiſhly quarrell, or maliciouſly hate, murthereth himſelfe, although he killeth not his Aduerſary: let the Act be wanting, the deſire will kill, and there may bee man-ſlaughter, where there is no ſhedding of bloud. 'Twas a witty ſpeech of one of your auncient De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamators,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ib. <hi>1.</hi> de Civ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cap. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> regiſtred by <hi>S. Auſtin,</hi> concerning <hi>Lucrece</hi> being rauiſhed by <hi>Tarquin: Duo fuêre, &amp; unus adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium commiſit.</hi> I know not whether the Act could bee committed without the ſinne, I am ſure the ſinne may
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1549:6"/> bee without the Act,<note place="margin">Et <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pado ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rit.</note> and an Eunuch may bee an Adulterer. Leſſe infirmities as well as great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties, will worke deſtruction; neither is it certaine that <hi>Aegypts</hi> little flyes were not her greateſt plague. The leaſt pricke in the leaſt ioint impoſtumateth the whole fleſh, but a moate in the Eye blindeth the ſight, a breach in the wall is the conqueſt of the enemie, and the ruine of the City: let vs not weigh our ſinnes, but number them, if they may ſeeme ſmall, wee cannot count them few. He that offendeth in one point of the Law, is guilty of all, <hi>Iames</hi> 2.10. Sinne like Hereſie, is of an encroaching nature; as one Hereſie proueth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo doth one ſinne vſher in another, the leſſer al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes making roome for the greater. Our vncatechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed trauailer iourneying into countries ſuperſtitious &amp; idolatrous, at the firſt is only vncouered, and boweth at the meeting of the Hoaſt, 'tis not good (ſaith he) to giue offence to them which are without; then he ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tureth to goe to their high places, to viſit their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Chappels, to heare and ſee their loud blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy in their Liturgies, and the profane pompe of their ceremonies; not that he intendeth a change of his Religion, but to purchaſe a ſounder hate of their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition: he no ſooner heareth &amp; ſeeth, but he liketh and approueth. Laſtly, as a ſure pledge of his Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, he returneth home, and ſeduceth others. The grand Hereſies of the Apoſtate Roman Church, which indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly and by conſequence raze and deſtroy the very foundation of Faith, came in by degrees, and the firſt ſtone for the building of <hi>Babel</hi> was laide long ſince. Traditions the Mother of all their Hereſies, had with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1549:7"/> them their right vſe, vntill firſt thoſe which were tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porarie and for a ſeaſon, were taught to be permanent and to endure for euer; then thoſe which were parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, and bound only ſome one Church, were made <hi>Catholick,</hi> generaly to enforce; after that, without exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, humane traditions had the ſame credit, the ſame Authority that diuine, Apotacticall as Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall: Laſtly all theſe were made as authenticall as the word written; giue the Pope a primacy, and he will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume a Principality; giue him more honour, and he will haue more power.</p>
            <p>As in doctrine, ſo in manners, ſmall things negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, grow and become big ones, the tares ſpring vp faſter then the corne, and they doe it inſenſibly, they ſteale their growth, <hi>creſcere non videmus, ſed creviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe;</hi> yet if this were not ſo, if leſſer ſlips opened not the ſluces for greater crimes to flow in; if wanton glances were not fore-runners of Fornication, nor Fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſtep to Adultery: if concupiſcence would not winne conſent, nor conſent breake out into Act, nor the Act often reiterated, beget an habit; yet were one and the leaſt of theſe damnable.</p>
            <p>Fleſh and Bloud may diſpute the faireſt praetexts for ſinne, yet black wil not be dyed into white. The Prince of darkneſſe when he tranſformeth himſelfe into an Angell of light, 'tis a iugling, and not a change; ſo the workes of darkneſſe may haue the credit of the deedes of light, they can neuer haue the goodneſſe: 'tis in vaine to ſow fig-leaues together to couer our deformities: let vs diſtinguiſh, and mitigate, colour, or qualifie what we can, that which is mortall, (and ſuch
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1549:7"/> is euery ſinne) will not be made veniall, otherwiſe eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Popiſh Caſuiſt, or Roman Schoolman would make veniall ſinnes as faſt as their God on earth doth pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. <hi>Poſſunt excuſari à mortali parentes,</hi> &amp;c. Parents putting off as well Nature as Religion, curſing their children euen to that height, that they wiſh them with the Diuell, ſinne but venially, ſo <hi>Greg. de Val.</hi> 3 Tome. 1090 page: <hi>Qui iudicium facit in re gravi temerari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, &amp;c.</hi> A Iudge iudging raſhly be it vpon life and death, ſinneth but venially. <hi>Bonacina</hi> in his ſecond diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation <hi>de peccatis,</hi> his 3 quaeſtion, <hi>puncto</hi> 5. Some ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſome theft muſt be veniall, when ſome blaſphemy, all if it be but chollerick, is not mortall, <hi>Navar</hi> in his Manuall, page 91. Yet doe theſe which thus preach im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punity for ſin, brand vs with the ſlaunder of Libertines. The diſtinction of mortall and veniall, vnderſtand it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, 'tis none of theirs, but ours: 'tis true, all ſinnes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of the Elect <hi>in foro iuſtitiae,</hi> in the rigour of iuſtice are mortall, but <hi>in foro miſericordiae,</hi> by the mercy of God, they are all veniall: legally all are mortall, Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelically all veniall; <hi>ratione peccatorum,</hi> they are all mortall, <hi>ratione peccantium,</hi> there are none not veniall; this is our doctrine, in which there is as well conſent as truth, with them there is no concord; for beſides ſome amongſt them which altogether deny their vſe of the diſtinction, as <hi>Gerſon</hi> and <hi>Fiſher,</hi> they cannot agree what this venial ſinne ſhould be: ſome will haue it <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra conſilium,</hi> others <hi>contra praeceptum;</hi> ſome ſtate it to be <hi>praeter legem,</hi> not <hi>contra legem,</hi> others graunt it to be againſt the Law, but not againſt charity which is the end of the Law; ſome thinke it both to be againſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1549:8"/> the Law, and to diminiſh charity; one will haue it to be ſinne imperfectly &amp; by analogy, others properly &amp; vnivocally; you may know 'tis <hi>Babel</hi> they are buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, by the confuſion of their language.</p>
            <p>While we thus proue all ſinnes to be mortall, we teach not a parity of offences; we are ſo Catholicke, that we are not Stoicall: all ſinnes are mortall, therfore all are aequall; 'tis bad Logicke: but calumnies muſt be prou'd by ſuch ſequels. Vertues haue their Climax, much more vices, the School giueth the reaſon; <hi>Illae ad unum tendunt, haec ab uno ad multas mundi vanitates.</hi> The perſon, the place, the manner, are circumſtances which both aggrauate &amp; extenuate a ſinne. Firſt <hi>the perſon,</hi> the perſon againſt whom we offend, &amp; the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon who offendeth: for the firſt, leſſe was the ſin of the vſurpers in ſlaying the ſeruants, then in killing the Heire of the Vineyard; far greater was the ſin of the Iewes in crucifying the Lord of glory, then that of their Fathers in murthering the Prophets: he ſinneth with a higher hand that tranſgreſſeth againſt the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of the firſt Table, then he that offendeth againſt them of the ſecond. Blaſphemie of oathes, &amp; profanation of the Sabbaoth, although here by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence of the Law, or by the conniuence of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, they eſcape the ſeuerity of diſcipline, ſhall hereafter be puniſhed with extremity of torture. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth the perſon only diſtinguiſh the guilt of the two Tables, but maketh degrees of ſin againſt one &amp; the ſame Commandement. Homicide &amp; Parricide are both murder, yet the ſeuere torture which all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions inflict vpon the one aboue the other, are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1549:8"/> euidence of the difference of the crimes. All mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is cenſured, is puniſhed with death, but death hath not alwaies the ſame ſting: when ſhe commeth to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture a Parricide, a <hi>Rauillac</hi> for murthering his King, O how ſhe is dreſſed like a Fury, armed with racks, with fires, with ſtrapadoes, with burning pincers, pulling off fleſh to make wounds; with ſcalding oile, pitch, &amp; ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen to powre into thoſe wounds, with horſes to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioint &amp; rent the body: &amp; that the malefactour may think himſelfe in Hell before he is dead, ſhe tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him in a furnace flaming with fire &amp; brimſtone, making vp her tragedie with the baniſhment of the Parricides parents, with pulling down the houſe where he was borne; &amp; although ſhe ſpareth the liues of his brethren, ſiſters, &amp; vnkles, yet muſt they change their names, &amp; all the <hi>Rauillacs</hi> muſt periſh. Degrees of puniſhment are as well after death as in death: the tortures of one damned ſoule are differenced from the pangs of an other; he that hath bin more wicked,<note place="margin">Mar. 23.15.</note> ſhall be more wretched, ſuch ſhall be the puniſhment as is the crime: which is augmented not only by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon who is offended, but by the perſon alſo who doth offend.</p>
            <p>Greatnes &amp; goodnes ſhould twin together, no Monarch hath licence to offend, no Prince hath any <hi>non-obſtante</hi> for ſin: neither yet is the Kings praeroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue leſſened, becauſe he may not ſin, it ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged if he could not ſin. 'Tis the miſery of ſoueraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that the offence is alwayes as great as the offender, the ſin as ſoueraigne as the perſon; a Prince his ſlips are crimes, a moat in his Eye is a beame; his blemiſh
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1549:9"/> is a leproſie; 'tis the Kings truth in the beginning of his firſt booke of his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: the reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he doth not ſo much commit his ſin, as teach it, <hi>nec tam delicto nocens eſt, quàm exemplo.</hi> A Peaſants ſin preſently findeth it's graue, &amp; is neglected as his perſon; but Monarchs vices are alwaies maſculine, and beget the like in others. Let <hi>Nero</hi> be ouer-much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in ſtageplaies, ſtraight the grauity of the Senat putteth on Buskins,<note place="margin">Lactant. <hi>5.</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiit.</note> and acteth a Comedy. <hi>Mores &amp; vitia Regis imitari genus obſequij putatur.</hi> Many doe thinke it againſt their allegiance, to be holy if their King be profane; The People will follow their Prince, yea although they forſake their God to doe it, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer <hi>Ioſuah</hi> their Captaine, their King, commandeth them, that will they doe, <hi>Ioſuah</hi> 1.16. Hence is it that the Iſraëlitiſh renegado Kings, with their damnable revolts ſo often apoſtated the whole land, and made the Iſraelites turne Idolaters. As all imitate their king, &amp; ſo aggrauate his ſinne, ſo doe moſt copie out his Nobles, &amp; augment their crimes. My Lord muſt haue his followers aſwell of his vice, as of his perſon; if he leaueth his King at the Chappell dore, he turneth not back without his Attendants, who if his Honour pleaſeth to be Idolatrous, wil wait vpon him euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Maſſe. As the Nobles &amp; Peers be ſo borne, ſo you honoured Lords who iudge the Land, &amp; you graue Fathers the Elders of the City, are ſo exalted, ſo pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, <hi>ut bona mala<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vestra ad Rempublicam pertineant,</hi> your vertues, and your vices are ſubiected &amp; inhaerent in your perſons; but by theſe (as the Heauens by their Influences) you worke good and euill through the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1549:9"/> whole Land. Better no Iudge in Iſrael then a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt one, no Elder then a wicked one; the firſt giueth but liberty, the ſecond addeth incouragement to ſin: you ſee to eminence of your perſons doubleth your crimes, and maketh your ſinnes as ſcarlet, as your ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits. I might inlarge my proofe and exhortation with an Apoſtrophe to the Clergy, the liuing Oracles of God, to whom ye muſt reſort for counſell. <hi>Hi ſi elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur magna &amp; non vivunt;</hi> if their liues cry not downe ſin as loud as their tongues, they may helpe to build the Arke, and periſh in the Floud: if they that preach the way to Heauen tread the way to Hell, Hell muſt be their portion, &amp; the number of their follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſhall add vnto their tortures: From the Clergy I might deſcend vnto the Gentry, from them to euery Oeconomicall Goueruour and Father of his family; &amp; although I ſtay there, yet let none the meaneſt here take heart to offend, for the ſin which the meanneſſe of his Perſon leſſneth by denying him followers, may be aggrauated by other circumſtances of the place and manner, which I will briefly glance ouer.</p>
            <p>We aſcribe no inherent holineſſe to any place, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel</hi> may become <hi>Bethauen;</hi> the Temple of God, the houſe of an Idol; the ſeat of <hi>Peter,</hi> the chaire of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt;</hi> neither doe I know whether the zeale of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome was right, if they warred for <hi>Iewry</hi> as for the <hi>Holy land;</hi> yet may we iuſtifie our conſecrated Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches &amp; Chappels, which being ſeparated for an holy vſe, may not be profaned; if the buyers and ſellers will trade in the Temple, our SAVIOVR prouideth a whip for them; and I would to God the zeale of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1549:10"/> in imitation of that of our God, would whip out the buyers and ſellers out of the Temple; would whip them either out of the Iles, or into the Quier. Good God, to ſee how the prophane walkers in the time of diuine ſeruice, when the Quier are chaunting their ſacred Anthems and Heauenly Halleluiahs, are then polluting the ſtones with their durty feete, when they ſhould weare them with their ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting knees; there are at the ſame time, ſome praying aboue, &amp; ſome blaſpheming below, and that ſo loud, that God heareth not the prayers for the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy.</p>
            <p>As the <hi>Vbi,</hi> the place, ſo the <hi>Quomodo,</hi> the manner of doing it doth much difference a ſinne. <hi>Mens &amp; propoſitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> ſaith the Law, <hi>diſtinguunt maleficia,</hi> who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer calleth his brother foole, is in danger of Hell fire, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.22. yet doth <hi>Paul</hi> call his brethren the <hi>Galatians fooles,</hi> and ſinneth not, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1. He that kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth a man ſhall ſurely be put to death, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 24.17. yet <hi>he that killeth a man ignorantly, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hated not before, ſhall flee vnto one of the Cities of refuge and liue, Deut.</hi> 19.4. &amp; 5. that which infirmity ſlippeth, muſt not be cenſured as that which malice acteth; that which is committed out of ignorance, is not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, as that which is done out of preſumption. I am no aduocate for ignorance; he who is ignorant, let him be ignorant ſtill, he who affecteth ignorance, let him periſh in his ignorance. In them that may know, it is a ſinne, in them that may not know it is a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for ſinne; it is to none which ought to know, (and all ought) a priuiledge to ſinne: yet if it be <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularis,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:1549:10"/> and not <hi>Vniuerſalis,</hi> as the Philoſopher; <hi>facti</hi> and not <hi>iuris,</hi> as the Lawyer, <hi>inuincibilis,</hi> and not <hi>vincibilis,</hi> as the Maſter of the ſentences, it doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe <hi>à tanto,</hi> although not <hi>à toto,</hi> it leſneth the offence, but taketh it not away; it ſtill remaineth a ſinne, and therefore liable to the puniſhment of ſinne, <hi>Death,</hi> which is the ſecond part in my <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>There is a death vnto ſinne, as well as a death for ſinne; a death which putteth not Nature in her graue, but Vice: how ſhall we being dead to ſinne, liue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.2. Death for ſinne is either ſpirituall, and of the ſoule; naturall and of the body; or eternall both of ſoule and body: <hi>Anima est vita, &amp; habet ipſa ſuam vitam,</hi> as the ſoule is the life of the body, ſo is God the life of the ſoule. <hi>The iuſt doe liue by faith, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, chapter</hi> 1. <hi>verſe</hi> 17. Euen <hi>by faith in the Sonne of God, Galat. chap.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 20. <hi>Who quickneth them with his ſpirit, Eph.</hi> 2.5. The body may liue, and yet the ſoule may be dead, by which the body liueth: there are ſome long ſince buried, which yet liue, ſuch are <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob;</hi> for God which is their God, is not the God of the dead but of the liuing; ſo there bee now ſome liuing which haue bin long ſince dead. <hi>A wi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dow liuing in pleaſure, is dead while ſhe liueth;</hi> the 1 of <hi>Timoth.</hi> 5. and 6. <hi>You that liue in ſinne, are already in your graues;</hi> I muſt therefore beſpeake you, as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time <hi>Chriſt</hi> did <hi>Lazarus, Lazare veni for as,</hi> come you forth of your graues, ariſe from death to life, from ſinne to newneſſe of life: but my words want efficacy, and my ſpeech hath no power to raiſe you; Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus therefore ſpeak that vnto your hearts, which I doe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1549:11"/> vnto your eares.<note place="margin">De eo quod de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terius potiori inſidiari ſolcat.</note> Where it is in the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Philo</hi> the Iew would haue vs read, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; for ſaith he, <hi>Cain</hi> had no ſooner ſlaine his brother, but he became dead himſelfe; and <hi>Abel</hi> being murthered, was yet aliue: if hee was not, how did hee ſpeake, how did he ſpeake aloude and cry for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance? ſo hee wittily. <hi>Let the dead bury the dead, Matth.</hi> 8.22. let them which are ſpiritually dead, bury them which are dead to nature, and the ſolemnity of their funerals being ended, let them prouide for their owne interrring which is at hand, for <hi>mors operata erit mortem,</hi> the death of the ſoule will cauſe the death of the body.</p>
            <p>A death common vnto all; it is all mens pilgrimage from the ſepulcher to the ſepulcher, from the graue of the wombe, to the graue of the earth; all men ſhall once die, for as much as all men haue ſinned, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27. The inſtinct of nature, which prompteth euery creature to ſeeke it's owne preſeruation, ſhould teach man not to make loue to death, not to wooe his owne deſtruction: although he tranſgreſſeth not the Law made againſt robbers who cutteth his owne purſe, yet he is guilty of murder who cutteth his owne throat: and ſurely he loueth murder who will act it vpon himſelfe, and yet ſuch are all ſinners, whoſe ſinnes are the weapons with which they butcher themſelues: like <hi>Saul</hi> and his Armor-bearer, they fall and die vpon their owne ſwords. If any ſonne of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth it to be preiudiciall to their health, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched Drunkard will abſtaine from his cups, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1549:11"/> the luxurious Epicure will faſt from his dainties: how fooliſh are they who would ſhunne death, and yet worke wickedneſſe which cauſeth death? There is no other cauſe of death but ſinne, where there is no ſinne, there is no death, no death of the body, no death of Nature.</p>
            <p>And yet he who had no ſinne, the Sonne of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, had his ſetting as well as his riſing, and walked into the Weſt; <hi>Licet naturae dominus, carnis tamen quam ſuſceperat legem non recuſauit;</hi> ſo that life it ſelfe dyed, yet not neceſſarily, but voluntarily, <hi>tradidit in mortem animam ſuam;</hi> neither was his death penall but expiatory, hee was not ſtung to death by ſinne, but he ſtung ſinne to death; by ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring death, he made death to ſuffer, and got the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by yeelding. <hi>O death where is thy ſting,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.55.56.</note> 
               <hi>O graue where is thy victory? the ſting of death is ſinne, and the ſtrength of ſinne is the Law, but thankes be vnto God which hath giuen vs victory through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt ſo deliuered his from death, as hee freed them from ſinne; which he ſuffered ſtill to dwell in them, although not to raigne ouer them. The <hi>Canaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> remaine in the land to proue the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> ſinne muſt inhabite in the regenerate, to encreaſe and try their faith: ſift them, you ſhall finde them ſo enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that they ſit in darkeneſſe, ſo purged that they muſt be cleanſed, their faith is mixed with infidelity, their wiſedome ioyned with folly, and their glory eclipſed with ſhame; to want ſinne muſt be a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans wiſh, it cannot be his hope, otherwiſe hee that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1549:12"/> muſt alwayes here be militant, ſhould ſometime be triumphant. We may be dead to ſinne, but ſinne will not be altogether dead to vs: we may cut it off, but it will bud againe; we may chaſe it away, but it will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne; we may quench it, but it will flame againe; it ſtill approacheth, it ſtill entiſeth and prouoketh vs; it ſtill ſtriueth, but it is to encreaſe our victory: at laſt it muſt haue the fall, and be triumphed ouer; ſo may the tyrant weepe to ſee himſelfe proſtrate at the feete of them who were his Captiues, <hi>Et ad eorum trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phum de quibus diù triumphaverat, ſe veteranus hoſtis perveniſſe deploret.</hi> Sinne is not ſo in the Elect, as it is in the reprobate; theſe either by habit, or reſolution, or diſcourſe, are incorporated into euill, and ſinne is naturalized in them: the other may ſometime be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed by force of paſſion, but their vnderſtanding ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome giueth conſent: the firſt ſerue ſinne, the other giue it only houſe-roome, or if they doe it any ſeruice, 'tis as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſerued <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> or as his Gally-ſlaues ſerue the Turke; by compulſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Damnatum eſt peccatum ſi non extinctum.</hi> Sinne hath loſt it's dominion, although it be not caſt out; ſo death is diſ-armed, although ſhe be not remoued; ſhe hath loſt her ſting, although ſhe keepeth her eſſence: nay, ſhe hath loſt her eſſence, the forme, the life of death is loſt, and ſhe is but equivocally what ſhe was before. As ſhe hath loſt her nature, ſo hath ſhe chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged her name; to die now, is but to ſleepe, to reſt, or be at peace. Death to the Elect is but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (as <hi>Nyſſen</hi> ſtileth it) it doth not ſo much puniſh, as purge and expiate ſinne, 'tis a Snake without her
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1549:12"/> ſting, a gaole-deliuery, an earneſt-peny of the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, a bridge to paſſe from corruption to incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to be wiſhed of all that wiſh to goe to Paradiſe, not to be feared at all, becauſe it freeth vs from all that is to be feared.</p>
            <p>A curious workeman ſeeing his Image of braſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>&amp;c. Epiph.</hi> in his 2 Booke. <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus Haereſes.</hi>
               </note> on which he hath beſtowed his Art and induſtry, to be ſpotted and defaced, he putteth it againe into the fire and new caſteth it, which is not the loſſe, but the perfection of the Image; ſo God after hee had made man a moſt elegant fabricke, ſeeing him polluted with ſinne, reſolued him againe into duſt, that he might riſe vnſpotted. When the veſſell that the Potter made was marred, he made of it another veſſell, <hi>Ier.</hi> 18.4. Cannot I doe with you as the Potter with his clay, ſaith the Lord? behold, as the clay is in the Potters hand, ſo are yee in my hand, O ye houſe of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> the ſame chapter and the ſixt verſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Non interit quiſquis victurus moritur.</hi> This death of Nature is rather a change then a death, 'tis not fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, <hi>quem putas interitum, ſeceſſus eſt;</hi> neither is it totall, 'tis onely of the body: death is dieted like the ſerpent, and can eat nothing but duſt; nay, 'tis not ſo much the death of the body,<note place="margin">Plin. Ep. lib. <hi>2.</hi> epiſt. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> as of the corruption of the body, <hi>Et mortalitas magis finita eſt quam vita.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Iſiod. Peleuſ: lib. <hi>4.</hi> epiſt. <hi>52.</hi>
               </note> Happy Martyrs, how their torments pleaſed them! how they kiſſed the fagot! and hug'd the fire, as though like <hi>Eliah,</hi> they had gone to heauen in fiery chariots! weigh their tortures, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1549:13"/> reade their conſtancy, you would iudge them to haue beene ſpirits without fleſh; if they might ſeeme to be afflicted becauſe they were heard to pray, they muſt be iudged to haue beene merry in their afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe they ſung Pſalmes. Their note was the ſame, although their pangs were differenced, with the three children in the fiery furnace;<note place="margin">Hieron.</note> 
               <hi>Qui inter frigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos flammarum globos hymnos edidêre pro fletibus.</hi> They wept not out an Elegy, as if they had beene pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring for their funerals: but they ſung and reioyced, as if it had beene their birth day, and it was their birth day to eternity. Bleſſed Martyres! for if they be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed who die in the Lord, bleſſed muſt they bee who die for the Lord. God ſaith to man, <hi>If thou ſinnest thou dyeſt, Gen.</hi> 2; but he beſpeaketh the Martyr, if thou refuſeſt to die,<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> thou ſinneſt. <hi>Quod tunc timen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum fuerat vt non peccaretur, nunc ſuſcipiendum eſt ne peccetur.</hi> Death which is the puniſhment of the Sinner, ſuffer it for Gods ſake, 'tis the glory of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate. <hi>Et cùm ſit mors peccati retributio, aliquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do impetrat vt nihil retribuatur peccato:</hi> As the wicked make bad vſe of the Law which is good; ſo doe the righteous make good vſe of death, which is bad; <hi>Ipſa poena vitiorum tranſit in arma virtutis, &amp; fit iuſti meritum etiam ſupplicium peccatoris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This made the Primitiue Chriſtians ſo ambitious of Martyrdome, that they did purſue their perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſo couetous of ruine, that not ſtaying for the hand of the hangman, they turned their owne executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and left their liues now in the fire, now in the water, like the man his lunaticke ſonne in the Goſpell;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1549:13"/> who being poſſeſſed with a Diuell, fell ſometimes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fire, and ſometimes into the water, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.14. 'Tis one thing for death to come to vs, 'tis another thing for vs to goe to death; the firſt may be martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the ſecond is murder. We muſt goe with ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity, but we muſt ſtay vntil we are called; death which is iuſt in the will, is vniuſt in the hand; we may not meet it, although we may attend it: inſomuch that it is an argument of force enough to proue the Bookes of the Maccabees to be Apocryphall, becauſe they doe ſo much extoll <hi>Razis</hi> the Father of the Iewes for mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering himſelfe.<note place="margin">2 Maccab. 14, 42.</note>
            </p>
            <p>As the true Chriſtian Martyrs be the beſt of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, ſo be your Pagan Pſeudo-Martyrs the worſt of the Heathen; other Idolaters doe but worſhip falſe gods; theſe goe about to proue them true,<note place="margin">Epiph. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Her. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> &amp; of theſe there were a number, euen vnto a Sect.</p>
            <p>Litle better then theſe were the Pſeudo-Catholicks if they ſuffred for their Haereſies, but indeed they die malefactors, more for ſedition, then Religion; more for faction, then for Faith; they liue Papiſts, but they are hanged Traitors; &amp; although both Haereſie &amp; Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon might deſerue death, yet hath the mercy of our Princes inflicted it only vpon the latter: God will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward both, &amp; euery ſin, euen the leaſt, with death; not with the firſt death only, but with the ſecond; not with naturall death only of the body, but with aeternall alſo both of body and ſoule for euermore.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vita hîc aut amittitur, aut tenetur.</hi> Euery one that departeth this life is either ſung into bliſſe by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, or hauled into torments by the diuels.<note place="margin">Cypr. de mort. ſect. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1549:14"/> were vnacquainted with the new Orcography of the School-men, whoſe ſearching invention hath founded as many Regions below the Earth, as there are aboue in the Aire; the firſt is their <hi>Limbus Patrum,</hi> where they faigne the Fathers to haue ſuffred the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary pain of loſſe before Chriſt's comming;<note place="margin">Tert. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cont. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cion.</note> an Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie borrowed from <hi>Marcion.</hi> and grounded vpon this falſe reaſon, that Heauen gates were ſhut vntill Chriſt's aſcenſion, which being diſprooued by the theeue's entrance, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> taketh the Keies, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth them at his Paſſion, and before they were not open; but then was his Paſſion when he was ſlaine, which was from the beginning of the world.</p>
            <p>The ſecond place is their <hi>Limbus Infantum,</hi> where they lodge Infants dying before Baptiſme, where they torture them with eternall paine of loſſe.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 17.12</note> A bloody concluſion of a mercileſſe Religion, which maketh not death (as it is here) a puniſhment for ſin, but ſin it ſelf; 'tis fooliſh to thinke, that the ſeed of the faithfull who are holy from their birth, ſhould be depriued of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward grace, becauſe neceſſity denyeth them the vſe of outward Sacraments; when publick Baptiſme may not be had, priuate is ſufficient; if death preuent this, votall will availe. <hi>Sat eſt ſi adeſt mentalitèr, cùm non poteſt haberi ſacramentalitèr;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thom. part. <hi>5.</hi> queſt. <hi>68.</hi> art, <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> it is enough if Chriſtian Parents deſire it, if they cannot obtain it. The force of truth made M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hooker</hi> of this opinion, euen where he diſputeth againſt Schiſmaticks for priuate Baptiſme. If there were not ſtrength of proofe, charity ſhould make them rather partiall,<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſt. polit. lib. <hi>5.</hi> ſect. <hi>61.</hi>
               </note> then cruell Iudges, &amp; force them to conclude, that many Infants of beleeuing pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1549:14"/> as they ſuffer no paine of ſenſe, ſo doe they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe no ſenſe of paine.</p>
            <p>The third place is their Purgatory, that Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phall dreame, that Roman mythology,<note place="margin">Dial. lib. <hi>4.</hi> ca. <hi>41</hi>
               </note> a place firſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to be built by <hi>Gregory</hi> ſix hundred yeares after Chriſt, vpon the falſe &amp; diſproued foundation of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall ſins; but they pretend more antiquity,<note place="margin">Dionyſ. Eccl. Hier. cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> &amp; would proue it by this falſe illation, becauſe there was prayer for the dead, whereas this prayer was not a ſupplicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but a thankſgiuing, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; or if they did peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 'twas not for the ſoule's ſafety, but the bodies glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; or if they ſupplicated for the ſoule, for the remiſſion of the ſins of the ſoul, 'twas only for a publick iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for a ſolemne acquittal and perfect conſummation of bliſſe: and this not becauſe the euent was doubtfull, but as <hi>Auſtin</hi> prayed for his Mother her entrance into Heauen, although he beleeued ſhe was entred before,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>9.</hi> Confeſſ. cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> and endeth his Petition with <hi>Credo Domine iam fece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris quod te rogo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a fourth place which theſe men deſerue to inhabit for inventing the other three, which is Hell, the place of the damned, where they ſuffer death, a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death, a death after death, a death and yet euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. The reprobate like the Salamander, is ſtil ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in the fire, but neuer conſumed; the ſoule ſuffreth of the body, but dieth not, ſo is the body tormented by the fire, but periſheth not: <hi>Illic ſapiens ignis membra urit &amp; reficit; carpit &amp; nutrit;</hi> like vnto the lightning which is the thunders fire, it ſo toucheth the bodies,<note place="margin">Minutius in Dial. Octa.</note> that it deſtroyeth them not, and if the fuell remain, the fire will ſtill endure. The flames of <hi>Aetna</hi> and <hi>Veſuvius</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:1549:15"/> ſtill burne, but neuer burne out; <hi>Ita poenale illud incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium non damnis ardentium paſcitur, ſed inexeſâ cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum laceratione nutritur.</hi> I diſpute not whether this fire be materiall or metaphoricall, whether it be ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall or corporall, certainly 'tis furious and terrible. I deſire neither to vnderſtand nor vndergoe it: yet thus much is certain, as it hath extremity of heat to torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſo hath it no light to comfort; it burneth, but ſhineth not: how painfull it is to ſit, how diſmall to ſuffer in darknes. There is no puniſhment but it is in Hell, there is no ſenſe-afflicting torture, but it is there augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: and yet doth the paine of loſſe far ſurmount the pain of ſenſe; tis more affliction to be ſhut out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, then to be impriſoned in Hell; and baniſhment is worſe then death: and yet ſhall this alſo be inflicted on ſin, both theſe, both without intermiſſion; to make Holy-daies in Hell, were to poëtize with <hi>Prudentius,</hi> both without end; for that <hi>Traian</hi> was deliuered from Hell by the prayers of Pope <hi>Gregory,</hi> I beleeue not, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Damaſcen</hi> bringeth the Eaſt &amp; Weſt to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe it.<note place="margin">Damaſ. ſerm. de defunctu. Auguſt de civit, Dei lib. <hi>21.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>24</hi>
               </note> This were with <hi>Origen</hi> to be kindly mad, and to turne Hell into Purgatory, both theſe, both with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermiſſion, both without end; and yet is the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment as iuſt as great: for death, euen this death is the ſtipend and wages of ſin, there is a proportion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the puniſhment and the offence, which is the third part of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>Facinus eſt menſura paenae;</hi> when miſdemeanour is cenſured with death, when the malefactor ſuffreth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the rigour of the Law, 'tis cruelty doometh him, and not Iuſtice; yet muſt the ſentence alwayes ballance
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1549:15"/> the crime; if the ſin be impudent, the puniſhment muſt be exemplary as is the offence, and an extraordinary offender muſt not be hanged vpon a common gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes. God his doome is alwayes impartiall, and he doth ſtill proportion his vengeance with the ſinne: he bleſſeth and curſeth, he rewardeth and puniſheth <hi>in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalogo;</hi> ſo that the vertue is charactred in the reward, and the vice may be read in the puniſhment. When God promiſeth to build <hi>Dauid's</hi> Houſe for euer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he purpoſed to build God an Houſe: when <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph's</hi> brethren doe homage vnto him as vnto their Lord, becauſe they had ſold him as their ſlaue: God ſo rewardeth them both, that he ſheweth the piety of the one, and the affliction of the othet. <hi>Ahab</hi> is humbled, and God deferreth his iudgments, the reward ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his humiliation, and ſheweth it to be temporary. Becauſe <hi>Vriah</hi> falleth by <hi>Dauid's</hi> ſword,<note place="margin">Optatus lib. <hi>2.</hi> cont. Parme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian.</note> the ſword muſt not depart from <hi>Dauid's</hi> Houſe, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the prophane Donatiſts doe impiouſly caſt the Sacramentall Bread vnto the dogges, the ſame doggs doe preſently teare in pieces thoſe Donatiſts: Becauſe <hi>Sodome</hi> burneth with flames of luſt, it is burned with flames of fire, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.24: becauſe the luſt is vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, the fire is ſupernaturall, and God ſendeth Hell fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Heauen. When you ſee <hi>Abſalom's</hi> haire to be his hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, you may know it was his pride; and when ye read that <hi>Salomon's</hi> Kingdome was diuided, ye may read, (and yet ye need not read to know it) that he diuided God's Kingdome. The line is no otherwiſe laid to the rule, then God's rewards and puniſhments are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned to our workes, many times thus in ſpeciall,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1549:16"/> &amp; in this life, ſo that (as the caſuiſts obſerue) he puniſhes in the ſame maner, in the ſame kind, in the ſame place, in the ſame part, but alwayes in generall &amp; hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.</note>As there are here degrees of grace, ſo ſhall there be hereafter degrees of glory. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one ſtarre differeth from another in glory: ſome ſhall but ſhine with the brightnes of the firmament, others ſhall gliſter with the glory of the ſtarres. All the Elect ſhall build vp the Houſe of God; but the Martyrs on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhall be pillars in the Houſe, <hi>Apocal.</hi> 2.12. All the Saints ſhall iudge the world, but the Apoſtles ſhall be mounted vpon twelue more eminent Thrones. All the Elect after iudgment ſhall ſit in Heauen; but ſome with ioy only on the left hand; others both with ioy and preheminency on the right. In Heauen there are many Manſions, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.2. And though he cannot lodge amiſſe who lodgeth there, yet is one roome more glorious then another. If there be not many manſions in Hell, if the roomes be not diſtinguiſhed, I am ſure the tortures are. Hell fire is all of one heat, yet doth it not burne alike. The ſame ſcorching Sun heat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a Northerne man more then a Southerne; yea an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man trauailing into <hi>Spaine,</hi> doth iuſtly more feare a <hi>Calenture</hi> then a <hi>Spaniard.</hi> Let ſtraw &amp; wood be the fuell of our fire, the heat is more and leſſe. The fuell of this fire are the ſinnes of the Reprobate; as they are ſmall or great, more or few, the heat is aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented or diminiſhed; but yet it is alwayes intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. See the proportion; when the leaſt ſin is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, an infinite Maieſty is offended, and therefore an infinite puniſhment muſt be inflicted. In the leaſt ſinne,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1549:16"/> God is contemned: and the creature praefer'd before the Creator:<note place="margin">Suarez de legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus lib. <hi>3. 8.</hi> num. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> Let <hi>Suarez</hi> diſtinguiſh <hi>mandatum à manda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te; Legiſtatorem à lege:</hi> there muſt be <hi>contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus perſonae,</hi> where there is <hi>contemptus operis:</hi> and if God be contemned, let it be materially or formally, directly, or indirectly; Simply, or <hi>ſecundum quid:</hi> Let them modificate it with more not to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood Metaphyſicall ſuttleties, the ſinne muſt ſtill be infinite, and the guilty muſt ſuffer torments in propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: which becauſe they cannot doe, <hi>Intenſivè ſimul &amp; ſemel:</hi> they muſt doe <hi>extenſivè &amp; ſucceſsivè.</hi> 'Tis no diſproportion when he that ſinneth but for a time, doth ſuffer more then for a time: hee would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes haue liued in ſinne, who neuer left to ſinne while he liued. And 'tis proportion that hee ſhould neuer want puniſhment, who had a will euer to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend. You ſee the Iuſtice, yet is not God more ſtrict in fitting the puniſhment to the ſinne, then certaine in auenging the ſin with the puniſhment, which is the fourth and laſt part of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>If neither Vertue ſhould be rewarded, nor Vice puniſhed, we might with <hi>Epicurus</hi> conclude both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and prouidence; yet were the perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Chriſtians weakely vrged by <hi>Caecilius</hi> in <hi>Minutius</hi> againſt their beliefe.<note place="margin">In Dial. Oct.</note> And his <hi>Dilemma</hi> (that their God either could not, or would not ſuccour them; and ſo that he was either weake or vniuſt) was but a flouriſh, and therefore he might haue ſpared his Sarcaſticall Interrogatory triumph: <hi>Qui ſubvenire reviviſcentibus poteſt, viventibus non poteſt? ſaevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia non eſt, ſed certamen:</hi> The fightings without, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1549:17"/> the terrours within, which the Saints vndergoe, are their trials, and not their puniſhments; and doe more exerciſe, then hurt then. Perſecution is not alwayes the inſtrument of God's fury, but ſometimes of his mercy. They are baſtards and not ſonnes who were neuer corrected: The father ſeeing his childe ſwou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, lendeth him a blow to recouer him: The Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian putteth his Patient into an Ague, that hee may cure him of a worſe malady. God ſometimes caſteth downe, that he may raiſe vp: hee ſometimes killeth, that he may make aliue: and turneth the poyſon to a preſeruatiue: <hi>Sicut ignis flatu premitur ut creſcat, &amp; vnde quaſi extingui cernitur inde roboratur.</hi> God then wreſtled with <hi>Iacob,</hi> when he came to bleſſe him: and put out <hi>Saul's</hi> eyes, that he might reſtore him his ſight. Let me be perſecuted, O Lord, ſo I be not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken: let me feele the laſh of thy blowes, ſo I eſcape the ſmart of thy fury: ſo if I be whipped, I will kiſſe he rod.</p>
            <p>As the iuſt doe thus enioy their afflictions, ſo doe he vniuſt ſuffer in their proſperity, and are curſed with their bleſſings:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ern. in Cant. Hom. <hi>42.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Certè tunc magis iraſcitur De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, cùm n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n iraſcitur.</hi> God's hand is then heauieſt on the wicked, when it is lighteſt; and it is their plague, that they are not plagued. <hi>Veniet ad faelices ſua portio, &amp; quiſquis vid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tur dimiſſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>dilatus eſt.</hi> Theſe happy worldlings muſt at laſt haue their iudgement; and their iudgement will be their damnation. Our ſinnes are our debts vnto God, and his iudgements are his debts to our ſinnes: where God oweth, he can, he will repay. He is not like the Heathen's Iupiter, that his
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1549:17"/> Quiuer ſhould be empty, that want of thunder-bolts ſhould diſ-arme him: The Lord of hoſtes cannot want Souldiers to fight his battels: If men of Warre ſhould be lacking, he hath an army of Frogges, and another of Lice, to diſcomfite and deuoure both <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and <hi>Herod.</hi> As the wicked doe multiply their tranſgreſſions, ſo doth he cumulate his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: and waſheth away a deluge of ſinne, with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge of water. He who is omnipotent, is no more powerfull then iuſt: and 'tis as certaine that he will, as that he can reuenge; ſometimes his wrath is ſlow, and not vpon the necke of the ſinne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 25.8.</note> as <hi>Phineas</hi> ſlew <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cosbi,</hi> in the very act of incontinency; yet it alwayes at laſt ouertaketh it: and then as hee hath beene ſlow to wrath, ſo will he be ſlow to lay downe his wrath; when he hath leaden heeles, then hee hath iron hands. So that the ſinner might wiſh that the blow came ſooner, ſo it came lighter.</p>
            <p>God iudgeth not like man: our Courts of Iuſtice doe cenſure onely knowne and open Malefactors: The Iudge at the laſt day will puniſh, the moſt cloſe and ſecret offenders: Heere the hired eloquence of the vnconſcionable Aduocate, or the falſe periury of the ſuborned witneſſe, ſometimes caſteth a miſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eyes of the Iudge, that he cannot ſee: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times corruption hood-winkes him, that he will not ſee: The Iudge at the generall Aſſiſe, ſhall be his owne euidence; he ſhall be Iudge, and Iury, and Witneſſes: <hi>Ipſe eſt qui videt, &amp; vnde videt.</hi> Hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat made the eye, ſhall not hee ſee? and he that made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he heart, ſhall not hee vnderſtand? And as hee can
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1549:18"/> both ſee and vnderſtand what he will, ſo will hee ſee and vnderſtand what hee can. There none may eſcape, heere ſo few are cenſured, that moſt are not quaeſtioned.</p>
            <q>Ille crucem ſceleris pretium tulit, hic Diadema.</q>
            <p>Heere you may ſee the petty thiefe, whoſe accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (and that perchance falſe) is but petty larciny, with chaines of iron about his feete; when the grand-thiefe, the ſtate-theife, who by fore-ſtalling, ingroſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, or by worſe means, robs the common-wealth; hath no chaines but of gold, and them about his neck. Such are your ſacrilegious Lay-Patrons, thoſe ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all robbers, and our Iewiſh oppreſſing Vſurers: The firſt, back't by the authority of the Law, begin now to confront the Pulpit, to quaeſtion the zeale of the Prieſt denouncing Gods iudgements againſt them, and to threaten puniſhment if they cannot inflict it: ſo that 'tis much ſafer to commit ſinne, then to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue it. Let them therefore enioy their conqueſt, let them triumph that they may rob God freely; At laſt their puniſhment will ouer-take them. <hi>Quis enim laeſos impune putabit—Eſſe Deos?</hi> The Vſurer hath no Law on his ſide, yet doth he praetend ſome, and where he findeth a tolleration, there doth the couetous Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny-father conclude an allowance. Turne to the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes made againſt this Citty-ſinne, and you ſhall finde it tolerated with an inhibition; for the Acts which ſeeme to allow it, doe ſome of them plainely praeface, that Gods Law condemneth it.</p>
            <p>And God will one day take an account of his Law, and that with farre more terrour then he deliuered it;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1549:18"/> At the deliuery hee did but ſhew how fearefull hee could be, at the execution he will be as fearefull as he ſhewed to be: when he ſhall be a Iudge he will inflict death, which he did but threaten when he was a Law-giuer. The day will come as certaine, as it is vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine when it will come. <hi>Behold the day commeth which ſhall burne like an Ouen, and all that doe wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhall be as ſtubble, and the day that commeth ſhall burne them vp ſaith the Lord of Hoſtes.</hi> Then ſhall the malignant ſpirit which tempted to ſinne, be a tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menter for ſinne: Then ſhall the amazed reprobate ſtand betweene his ſinnes accuſinng him, and God's Iuſtice terrifying him; below him ſhall be his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, aboue him his Iudge, and he equally trembling at the horrour of the one, and the wrath of the other: within him his conſcience, without him the world ſhall be on fire; <hi>Quid metuat qui ad iſta non trepidat?</hi> Who heareth this, and yet dareth to ſinne? what pleaſure of tentation can counteruaile this horrour of euent? who now is not frighted, who would not bee wonne from wickedneſſe? who now is not drawne, who could not be before allured vnto repentance? let vs therefore accept no obiect but of ſorrow: let vs, becauſe we are fallen by nature, haſten to ariſe by grace, that we may turne the ſentence, from <hi>Goe yee curſed,</hi> into <hi>Come yee bleſſed:</hi> that <hi>death</hi> may be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into <hi>life:</hi> this euerlaſting death, into eternall life, which is the firſt part in the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>To haue any conceit of life but good, is now as well impious as Stoicall; ſince eternall bliſſe is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to it. Yet doth this life of glory ſo farre ſurpaſſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1549:19"/> the life of nature, as the ſecond death is worſe then the firſt: Hence it is that many who feare not death, feare to die after death, and they who are hungry to looſe their liues, are yet afraid not to find them being loſt. I ſhould now from this mount, as God did from mount <hi>Nebo</hi> vnto <hi>Moyſes,</hi> ſhew you the land of <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> and diſcourſe of, though not expreſſe, the ioyes of this eternall life: Ioyes in number infinite, yet are they ſummed vp in the Beatificall viſion; and you might ſee them all, could you ſee God. How often hath the deuotion of many not ſuperſtitious Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims, with wearied paces meaſured the way from euery climate to <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> who haue recompenſed their tedious trauels, onely with the ſight of the ground which our Sauiour trode, and the viſitation of the Sepulcher where hee lay? how were the wiſe men rauiſhed with contentment, when the ſtarre had brought them to ſee Chriſt but in his Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle? when he came to be of age, and began to preach in the City; <hi>Videres referta tecta ac laboran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia:</hi> when he tooke houſe, there was ſuch a crowd that the ſicke of the palſie could not get in, except the houſe had bin vnroofed: when he iournied from <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, migravit ciuitas,</hi> the City was diſlodged, and ran out of the gates: The Sicke and all, <hi>Qui neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecto medentium imperio ad ſalutem ſanitatem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repebant:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plin. Paneg.</note> So that the concourſe of the people made a narrow way to Chriſt, as well as to Heauen: The preſſe was once ſo great, that there was no ground left for <hi>Zacheus</hi> to ſtand on: for he needed not to haue climed the tree, to looke downe vpon him that was
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1549:19"/> higher then the clouds. If theſe were happy, (and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py they were: happy were the eyes which haue ſeen that which you ſee, <hi>Luke</hi> 28.10) who thus ſaw Chriſt on earth, and in the forme of a ſeruant, happy muſt they be who ſhall behold him in Heauen, &amp; in his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. There muſt be all the obiects both of loue &amp; admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. There ſhall internall bliſſe be ioyned to exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall faelicity; where there ſhall be added the Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of his Diuinity, to the ſight of his Humanity. Then ſhall euery ſenſe inioy it's own delight; then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery faculty of the ſoule ſhall be fully ſatisfied; ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but not glutted: <hi>Vitae fontem &amp; ſitientes haurient, &amp; haurientes ſitient:</hi> There ſhall be hunger without want, abundance without loathing. The Saints ſhall ſtill haue what they deſire, but they ſhall ſtill ſee more to be deſired; what here we can neither in wiſh ſeeke, nor in imagination faine, there we ſhall beyond hope be poſſeſſed of: neither ſhall this ioy be more full then it ſhall be vniuerſall. Here one part of the Earth is not illuminated, but the other is darkned: The Sun ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not, but the Moon goeth down: All the Starres though they ſhine with the luſter of the Sun, yet can they not be ſeene for the luſter of the Sunne, ſo that they are eclipſed with their light. Here the ioy of one, occaſioneth and breedeth the ſorrow of another: there <hi>Et ſi diſpar ſit gloria ſingulorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſtin. med. cap. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>attamen communis eſt laetitia omnium.</hi> Me thinkes while I dilate of this glory, I find my ſelfe in the ſame temper with <hi>Peter, Iames,</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> thoſe three Diſciples when they ſaw a glimpſe of it in the tranſfiguration of CHRIST on mount <hi>Tabor,</hi> and muſt cry out with the firſt of them.<note place="margin">Math. 7.4.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; Tis good for vs to be here; and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1549:20"/> I would build Tabernacles too for your attentions to reſide in, but that my diſcourſe may not be like this life euerlaſting, which is the adiunct or Duration.</p>
            <p>The life of Nature if it be ſweet, yet it is ſhort, and if we may loue it, we cannot keep it; <hi>vivendo decreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, &amp; tranſeundo nosterit:</hi> So that our age beginneth not to encreaſe, before it decreaſeth. This life of glory is more glorious, becauſe it is laſting; if there were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thought of ending, there could not be a full power of inioying it. In Heauen there is no time, there is no diſtinction of time: there are no yeares, nor dayes, nor nights, or if there be, there is but one day, a day with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a night, <hi>Aeternitas unus dies aeternus eſt:</hi> and one day in thy Courts O Lord, as it is better, ſo it is longer then a thouſand. <hi>Conſideremus magnitudinem praemij, ſi conſiderari poſſit quod immenſum eſt:</hi> Let vs a little meditate on the vnlimited greatnes of this reward, &amp; we ſhall find, that no treaſure of our beſt workes can euer purchaſe it; 'Tis a reward, not of merit, but of mercy, not of debt, but of fauour. 'Tis ſo a reward, that it is a gift, which is the ſecond part of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>The words are in the originall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the gift or grace of God. The moderne Popiſh Schooles haue ſo highly magnified the arme of fleſh, and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly extolled the nature of mankind, that they haue blaſphemouſly oppoſed the grace &amp; mercy of Chriſt: See how the little wormes ſwell; ſee how corruption diſputeth for the freedome of the will: not for ſuch a freedome as <hi>Auſtin</hi> proued againſt the Manichees, or the Greek Fathers evinced from the Stoicall Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: They argue not that the will cannot be carried vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olently,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1549:20"/> but that it may be moued neceſſarily; neither is this neceſſity from which they would be freed, a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall or abſolute neceſſity; they hold it not enough that a man be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, except he may be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count not that freewill which dependeth vpon the free will of God. They place it in the indifferency of Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, giuing it ability to chooſe, to refuſe, good, or bad; &amp; that not only in things which are naturall &amp; morall, but in thoſe alſo which are ſpirituall:<note place="margin">Biel. <hi>3.</hi> ſent. diſt. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> ſtill making the liberty of the will as large as the obiect. Theſe are their blaſphemies, that the will is a faculty meerely Actiue; and this they conclude againſt their own <hi>Aquinas,</hi> that by their naturalls,<note place="margin">Suarez de au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xil. Diuin. grat. l <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>2</hi> num. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> they can doe workes acceptable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God; that without ſpirituall help, they can for the loue of God ſorrow for ſin; moſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> indeed towre not ſo high, but they require the helpe of <hi>exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting grace:</hi> Some outward only, ſo did <hi>Pelagius;</hi> ſome inward too, ſo did the <hi>ſemi-Pelagians;</hi> at leaſt to be profitable, if not neceſſary: and thoſe doe no more;<note place="margin">Ibid. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>4</hi> num. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> for they yeeld not any Phyſical efficacie or reall working by infuſing any power of conſent, but only a morall determination in propounding ſome obiect of feare or loue: they hold the neceſſity of grace, but they hold they merit the grace which is neceſſary: &amp; when 'tis offered, they may chooſe whether they will accept it: 'Tis in our power to reiect or receiue any inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſpirit: ſo the <hi>Tridentine</hi> Conventicle in their 6. <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>Canon,</hi> making grace <hi>Inſtar advenae,</hi> like a gueſt whom we may chooſe to let in; like a garment which we may refuſe to put on: like a ſuaſory or elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent oration, which we are not forced to conſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1549:21"/> They neuer ſpeak of grace and the will, but with blaſphemous ſimilitudes: They match them together, yea they ſometimes praeferre the laſt, making the will the agent, and grace to inſtrument. See <hi>Pelagius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned from Hell, only a little diſguiſed, and therefore the better able to ſeduce. What <hi>Maxentius</hi> ſomtimes ſpoke of <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> giue me leaue to conclude of theſe, <hi>Dum nolunt videri Pelagiani, accuratius Pelagij erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem fouent, quàm Pelagius pepererat:</hi> Vpon this grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of free-will, is built the proud Haereſie of the Roman merit, their immunity from ſin; not only from the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, but the guilt of ſin: their ſatiſfaction, a thing moſt derogatory from Chriſt's paſſion: the treaſure of their Church, the ſupererogated works of their Saints departed, are true corollaries from this falſe poſition: Religion cannot teach them how Chriſt's merits may be imputed to vs: Couetouſnes perſwadeth them that the merits of one man, may be conferred vpon another: And I belieue them in their tenet, the merits of one man may be conferred on another; the ſins of our fore-fathers may be viſited vpon vs their children; ſee our merits, <hi>Damnationis ſunt, non liberationis,</hi> they may caſt vs down to Hell, they cannot lift vs vp to Heauen.</p>
            <p>The ſacred volumes euery-where oppoſe theſe Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Phariſies in their high-towring thoughts of meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, ſtill throwing down this top of <hi>Babell,</hi> and with a criticall preciſenes giuing all vnto grace; <hi>When wee were children of wrath,</hi> Eph. 2.13. <hi>Enemies to God,</hi> Rom. 5.10. <hi>reprobate to euery good worke,</hi> the ſame E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. the 8.1. <hi>Then was our election of grace,</hi> Rom. 11.5.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1549:21"/> 
               <hi>our vocation was according to grace.</hi> 2 Timoth. 1.9. <hi>Faith was giuen vs,</hi> Philip. 1.29. and our iuſtification was <hi>gratis.</hi> Rom. 3.24. <hi>Nemo quicquam agit ad ſeipſum generandum;</hi> no man is his own father, and begetteth himſelf; 'tis as good diuinity concerning mans regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and ſecond birth, as it is Philoſophy concerning his firſt: and as we are iuſtified freely by grace, ſo by grace alſo ſhall we be freely glorified. Heauen will not be taken by violence, neither ſhall they who ſhall weare the Crown of bliſſe, euer win it; they ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be ſaued who will be their own Sauiours: we may inherit, we cannot purchaſe this Kingdome; by indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry we cannot, by birth we ſhall obtain it. <hi>Iacob</hi> might haue loſt the bleſſing, had he not put on the garments of his brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> and ſo ſhall we to, if we be not clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with Chriſt's righteouſnes, with the righteouſnes of our elder brother as with a garment.</p>
            <p>If our good workes were perfect, yet are they not our own; if they were our own, yet are they not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; if they were both perfect, and our own, yet could they not merit: ſtill the reward is of mercy, ſo ſaith the Law, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.6: ſo the Goſpel, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18. Our good workes are not our own, and Nature's great ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary his poſition is only true of the workes of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,<note place="margin">Ariſt. <hi>5.</hi> lib. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thic. cap <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hominem eſſe</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; we worke not, but God worketh in vs. <hi>Quoties enim bona agimus, Deus in nobis at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nobiſcum, ut ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remur, operatur;</hi> as it is in the 9 Canon of the 2 Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Arauſica:</hi> to which I add <hi>concilium Mileuitanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> the 5 Canon, becauſe it hath the approbation of two Roman Popes, <hi>Innocentius,</hi> and <hi>Caeleſtinus:</hi> Our works
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1549:22"/> are not perfect, the myrie channell muddeth the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which runneth through it; the vnclean veſſell ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the wine vnſauory which is within it: what God worketh in man, is blemiſhed by the pollution which is in man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tutiſſimum eſt fiduciam totam in ſolâ Dei miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiâ &amp; benignitate reponere, Bellarmine</hi> in his 5 book <hi>de Iuſtificatione,</hi> 7 chap. 3 propoſition: how? is it ſafeſt to put no confidence in merit, and yet is it no danger to teach merit? will they belieue that which they dare not hope? Chriſt hath merited our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he hath not giuen vs power to merit it, he hath ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfied and pay'd our debt, he hath not giuen vs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to pay or ſatiſfie; neither is our modeſty humble enough, if we confeſſe we haue receiued the power of meriting, except we deny all power to merit. The e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy of grace acknowledged that he had receiued his ſoule, and the faculties of his ſoule; his will, and the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of his will, from God; and yet was he ſtill an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to grace. So doe the Romaniſts ſtill oppoſe Chriſt's merits, although they deriue their power of meriting from his merits. If I would confirme this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine with the ſtrength of authority, I could cite a cloud of witneſſes, nurſed in their own Schoole, <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand, Pighius, Eckius, Gregorius Ariminenſis,</hi> all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in his 5 book <hi>de Iuſtificatione,</hi> 16 chap. to whom may be ioyned <hi>Marſilius, Ferus. Faber Stapulenſis, Stella,</hi> all rightly quoted by our reuerend Biſhop, in the 2 book of his Proteſtants appeale, 11 chap. beſides the many blots which their frequent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgations haue made in moſt of the auncient Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1549:22"/> and Fathers, which are as good teſtimonies as theſe mens writings: Nay, 'tis moſt true of Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelfe, which <hi>Kemnitius</hi> obſerueth of moſt of your Romiſh Doctors, that in this argument, as he is an hereticall diſputing Ieſuite, ſo is hee a moſt Orthodoxe meditating Proteſtant.</p>
            <p>Whoſe doctrine is not, as the Papiſt maliciouſly impoſeth, the vice of the Libertine; we teach indeed that the righteouſneſſe by which we are iuſtified, is not inherent but imputatiue; that it is not ours, but Chriſts; or if it be, 'tis made ours, and not within vs: that on our part faith onely is required, and that alſo' to be the gift of God. <hi>Elegit eos quos voluit gratuita dei miſericordia, non quia fideles futuri erant ſed vt eſſent, ijſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> gratiam dedit non quia fideles erant ſed vt fierent: Lombard</hi> in his firſt booke, and his 41 diſtinction. Yet doe we affirme that this faith which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone iuſtifieth, is neuer alone, <hi>Sola fides ſed non fides ſola,</hi> as the Schoole critikiſeth; faith iuſtifieth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out workes, and yet is not the faith which iuſtifieth without workes. Faith without workes is dead, and faith which is dead cannot giue life, eternall life. It muſt be liuely and actiue, operatiue and fruitfull; wee deny it to be faith in the Puritan phraſe, that is a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked faith; ſo that we require of our good workes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not a meritorious dignity to iuſtification, yet a dutifull neceſſity to ſanctification. God begetteth not children to the Diuels image: your carnall Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers, baſtard Chriſtians, and pſeudo-profeſſors, are ſo farre from being the ſonnes of God, that they are not his ſeruants. This is our doctrine, this our practice:
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1549:23"/> for (thankes be vnto God) our Land is almoſt as rich in charity as in wealth: ſuperſtition was neuer more bountifull then is Religion, witneſſe the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of our Founders and Benefactors, with new ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions now ſo enlarged, that the Preacher is forced to be vnthankfull, and cannot remember them. Our Colledges newly built, and now in building, our Lectures daily multiplied, our Libraries compleatly furniſhed, our poore better prouided for by charity then by Statute; and yet well by Statute, were the Statutes well executed. Our Hoſpitals lately Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and yet not ſo lately, but they begin already to be abuſed. I am afraide ſome of them are ſo ſicke, that it were charity to viſite them. You who haue power and authority, you whom God and our Benefactours haue made Viſitors and Ouer-ſeers of their liberality; let me beſeech you in the bowels of Chriſt Ieſus, that you would not ſuffer that which bounty hath giuen, to maintaine luxury, or that which hath beene dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated vnto God, to be conferred vpon them, who do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the deeds of darkneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that in the light, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe themſelues to be the children of the Diuell: ſo ſhall theſe houſes of piety be as richly endowed with your care, as with their Founders Revennues, and you ſhall be as bountifull as their Benefactors without expence. I haue now ſhewed you the way how eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life is conferred vpon vs, 'tis freely and by gift, 'tis but <hi>Aske and haue:</hi> and I make no quaeſtion but that ye are willing to petition for it, that therefore ye may know to whom to direct your ſupplications, I muſt ſhew you the Authour, who is God. Eternall life is
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1549:23"/> the <hi>gift of God,</hi> which is the third part of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of which is a ſyllable.</p>
            <p>Life as death is naturall, ſpirituall and eternall, there is a life of Nature, a life of Grace, and a life of Glory; and God who is the Prince and Lord of life, <hi>Acts</hi> the 3, and 15. is doner of them all. Firſt, of the naturall, <hi>In him we liue, and moue, and haue our being; Acts</hi> 17.28. Then of the ſpirituall, <hi>Neuertheleſſe I liue, yet not I, but Chriſt in me, Gal.</hi> 2.20. And laſtly, of eternall life here in my Text. And God heere is no one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but the whole Trinity, when the Creator confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a benefit vpon the creature; then as the Father giueth, ſo doth the Sonne; as both, ſo doth the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Opera Trinitatis ad extra ſunt indiviſa.</hi> You haue the Authour, of whom ye may with confidence beg it, with certainty obtaine it; for ye haue a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Mediator <hi>Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> But <hi>the gift of God is eternall life through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> which is my laſt part, of which in a briefe conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>Chriſt is our Mediatour, as he is God and man; God incarnate, the perſon, by a different act and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, but in one and the ſame perfection proceeding from both his natures, his humanity ſuffered, his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity ſatisfied, but that his humanity could ſuffer, could ſatisfie, was from his Diuinity. Had he bin one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man, the Iewes had neither reuiled, nor blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, when they ſcoffingly ſaid, <hi>He that ſaued others, let him ſaue himſelfe.</hi> We are neither <hi>Manichees,</hi> nor <hi>Arians;</hi> we neither deny the humanity, nor oppoſe the Diuinity; we embrace that of <hi>Timothy, Tim.</hi> 1.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1549:24"/> 2. and 5. <hi>There is one God, and one Mediator between God and man, the man Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> But we muſt haue S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> Commentary. <hi>Sed neque per ipſum libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remur vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mediatore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dei &amp; hominum homine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſum Chriſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> niſi eſſet &amp; Deus.</hi> In his <hi>Enchridion,</hi> his 108. Chapter: If Chriſt be Mediatour according to his God-head, then can none be mediatour who is not God; our Pſeudo-Catholickes are not more Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricall in any point then this; although they labour to diſtinguiſh themſelues into the truth, by ſaying they haue but one mediatour of redemption, although they haue more of interceſſion: one chiefe Aduocate, although many ſecundary, that their prayers are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected vnto God; <hi>Tanquam per eum implendae,</hi> to Saints onely, <hi>tanquam per eos impetrandae, Aquinas</hi> 2.2. the 83. quaeſtion, and the 4. Article; while they pretend they worſhip God in the Saints, they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Saints as God. Certainely their practice in this is worſe then their doctrine, and yet is their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine ſo bad, that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is aſhamed of it, and weakely excuſeth it, ſaying, Their words are not their meaning, <hi>De beatitudine ſanctorum,</hi> his 17, Chapter, and his 1. propoſition. I will not offend your eares with their blaſphemous phraſes, euery where inſerted in their Miſſals and Liturgies. <hi>Chriſtus,</hi> ſay they; <hi>caput gratiae Maria collum,</hi> and they ioyne her milke with his blood. I haue troden the Vine-preſſe alone, there was no man with me. <hi>Eſaw,</hi> the 63.3. true, no man but a woman there was, the bleſſed Virgin; ſo there ſottiſh, as well as blaſphemous gloſſe, 'tis not hee but ſhee, that ſhall breake the Serpents head, <hi>Gen,</hi> 3.16.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1549:24"/> not <hi>ipſe</hi> but <hi>ipſa;</hi> ſo 'tis tranſlated, ſo allowed by the graue Fathers of <hi>Trent.</hi> We are no more ſaued by <hi>Mary,</hi> then we were condemned by <hi>Eue;</hi> ſaluation is onely by Chriſt, <hi>Per Ieſum Chriſtum Dominum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum,</hi> though Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, as all our Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects runne, and by him wee ſhall be ſaued, hee hath a double right to this eternall life; the firſt by heritage, the other by conqueſt: the firſt for himſelfe; the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond for vs. Mercy hath giuen way to Iuſtice, and Innocency hath ſuffered; Iuſtice ſhall giue way to Mercy, and the guilty ſhall be ſaued. Let vs therefore begge with alacrity. <hi>Quid non dabit petentibus, qui ſeipſum dedit non petentibus?</hi> Giue vs O God, this eternall life, euen for thy Sonnes ſake, our Mediatour and Aduocate, Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 22. <hi>in marg. r.</hi> part. 3. <hi>p.</hi> 37. <hi>l.</hi> 25. <hi>r.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>in marg. r.</hi> lib. 3. cap. 5.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
